Guide to the Jeanne Mirer Papers TAM.383
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jeanne Mirer Papers
1967-1981
1972-1979
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mirer, Jeanne
TAM.383
20 Linear Feet in 40 manuscript boxes.
Jeanne Mirer practices labor, employment and civil rights law in New York City. She has been an active member of the National Lawyers Guild (NLG) since the 1970s, and has served in various capacities. She is currently the NLG International Committee Co-Chair, President of the International Association of Democratic Lawyers (IADL), a founding Board Member of the International Commission for Labor Rights, and a Board Member of the Sugar Law Center. Mirer has been an integral part of the founding and leadership of the International Commission for Labor Rights. She earned her J.D. from Boston University and B.A. from the University of Pittsburgh. Materials in this collection (bulk 1972-1979) document Jeanne Mirer's work in various positions of the National Lawyers Guild (NLG), as well as other national and regional committees that she was a part of, such as the Affirmative Action/Anti-Discrimination National Committee, the Minority Legal Resources Task Force (MLRTF), the Michigan Coalition to Overturn the Bakke Decision (MCOBD), and the National Committee to Overturn the Bakke Decision (NCOBD). The majority of Mirer's National Lawyers Guild materials pertain to her role as National Treasurer for the organization, and her work on the National Finance Committee (NFC). Materials include meeting agendas and minutes, correspondence, memos, reports, newsletters, circulars, subject files, ephemera, court transcripts, and legal briefs. The majority of the collection pertains to affirmative action, in particular, the cases of United Steelworkers of America v. Weber (referred to as Weber v. Kaiser in the collection), and Regents of the University of California v. Bakke. While much of her professional activism took place on a national level with NLG's National Office (NO) and National Executive Committee (NEC), Mirer also had very city-specific work in Detroit, Boston, and New York City. Some of the work that she did in these cities pertained to affirmative action, criminal justice reform, labor unions, and pollution.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in collection; provenance is unknown. The accession number associated with this collection is 1950.034.
Scope and Contents
Materials in this collection (bulk 1972-1979) document Jeanne Mirer's work in various positions of the National Lawyers Guild (NLG), as well as other national and regional committees that she was a part of, such as the Affirmative Action/Anti-Discrimination National Committee, the Minority Legal Resources Task Force (MLRTF), the Civil Liberties Union of Massachusetts, the Michigan Coalition to Overturn the Bakke Decision (MCOBD), and the National Committee to Overturn the Bakke Decision (NCOBD). The majority of Mirer's National Lawyers Guild materials pertain to her role as National Treasurer for the organization, and her work on the National Finance Committee (NFC). Materials include meeting agendas and minutes, correspondence, memos, reports, newsletters, circulars, subject files, ephemera, notes,, court transcripts, and legal briefs. The majority of the collection pertains to affirmative action, in particular, the cases of United Steelworkers of America v. Weber (referred to as Weber v. Kaiser in the collection), and Regents of the University of California v. Bakke.
While much of her professional activism took place on a national level with NLG's National Office (NO) and National Executive Committee (NEC), Mirer also had very city-specific work in Detroit, Boston, and New York City. Some of the work that she did in these cities pertained to civil rights, affirmative action, criminal justice reform, labor unions, and pollution.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
Jeanne Mirer practices labor, employment and civil rights law in New York City. She has been an active member of the National Lawyers Guild (NLG) since the 1970s, and has served in various capacities. She is currently the NLG International Committee Co-Chair, President of the International Association of Democratic Lawyers (IADL), a founding Board Member of the International Commission for Labor Rights, and a Board Member of the Sugar Law Center. Mirer has been an integral part of the founding and leadership of the International Commission for Labor Rights. She earned her J.D. from Boston University and B.A. from the University of Pittsburgh.
Civil rights -- United States.; Affirmative Action programs.; Affirmative action programs in education -- Law and legislation; Discrimination in employment -- Law and legislation -- United States; Discrimination -- Law and legislation; Collective bargaining.; National Lawyers Guild; National Lawyers Guild. National Office; Affirmative Action Coordinating Center; National Committee to Overturn the Bakke Decision (U.S.); United Steelworkers of America; Kaiser Aluminum and Chemical Corporation; Bakke, Allan Paul
- Newsletters, National Lawyers Guild (NLG), 1973-1978 (Box 1)
- Subject Files, Michigan Coalition to Stop S-1, 1974-1978 (Box 2)
- Affirmative Action, Michigan Coalition to Stop S-1, NLG National Office (NO), 1973-1976 (Box 3)
- NO, National Finance Committee (NFC), 1975-1977 (Box 4)
- NO, NFC, 1971-1977 (Box 5)
- NFC, Civil Liberties Union of Massachusetts (CLUM), 1970-1976 (Box 6)
- CLUM, Massport, Chelsea Pollution, 1972-1974 (Box 7)
- CLUM, NO, NFC, 1971-1975 (Box 8)
- Newsletters, Chelsea Pollution, CLUM, 1970-1975 (Box 9)
- Newsletters, Subject Files, 1968-1975 (Box 10)
- NLG, Employment and Academic Work, 1967-1976 (Box 11)
- NFC, Newsletters, 1972-1976 (Box 12)
- NFC, Affirmative Action/Anti-Discrimination (AA/AD) National Committee, 1977-1979 (Box 13)
- Affirmative Action, Wayne County Neighborhood Legal Services, 1976-1980 (Box 14)
- Affirmative Action, Coalition to Save the Detroit Human Rights Ordinance, Hampton vs. Hanrahan, 1974-1980 (Box 15)
- Lynn French, Minority Legal Resources Task Force (MLRTF), 1974-1976 (Box 16)
- MLRTF, 1975-1977 (Box 17)
- MLRTF, Subject Files, 1970-1979 (Box 18)
- Regional Conference Guild, NLG China Delegation, 1977-1978 (Box 19)
- NLG China Delegation, UAW, Labor Newsletters, 1973-1976 (Box 20)
- UAW, Labor Newsletters, International Committee, Police Misconduct Litigation, 1973-1976 (Box 21)
- NLG Committees, Newsletters, 1973-1978 (Box 22)
- Newsletters, 1973-1978 (Box 23)
- Newsletters, Affirmative Action Coordinating Center (AACC), Michigan Coalition to Overturn the Bakke Decision (MCOBD), 1974-1981 (Box 24)
- National Committee to Overturn the Bakke Decision (NCOBD), Anti Bakke Decision Coalition (ABDC), NLG China Delegation, Organized Workers of Legal Services Local 1 (OWLS), 1976-1979 (Box 25)
- OWLS, Status of Legal Services Legislation, 1976-1981 (Box 26)
- Affirmative Action, Wayne City Neighborhood Legal Services, 1975-1981 (Box 27)
- Bakke Amici Attorneys' Roundtable, 1977 (Box 28)
- Bakke Amici Attorneys' Roundtable Working Papers, Financial Materials, 1977-1979 (Box 29)
- Financial Materials, Bakke Subject Files, Conference Materials, 1977-1979 (Box 30)
- MCOBD, Speeches, Correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 31)
- Bakke, MCOBD, Weber v. Kaiser, 1977-1979 (Box 32)
- Weber v. Kaiser, 1978-1979 (Box 33, Box 34)
- Bakke, 1977-1978 (Box 35, Box 36)
- Bakke Amicus, 1976-1977 (Box 37)
- Subject Files, Committee Files, 1971-1975 (Box 38)
- NFC, Prison Conference, 1972-1975 (Box 39)
- Committee Files, 1974 (Box 40)